<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A display of the headpiece and codpiece valour of the most renowned Colonel Robert Jermy, late of Bafield in the county of Norfolk, esquire, with his son Captain Toll by his side, now on their way for New-England. Or the Lively description of a dead-hearted fellow, to the tune of a Turd, or the Black-smith.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1674A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.40.m.9.[73]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885280</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02716)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A3:2[74])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A display of the headpiece and codpiece valour of the most renowned Colonel Robert Jermy, late of Bafield in the county of Norfolk, esquire, with his son Captain Toll by his side, now on their way for New-England. Or the Lively description of a dead-hearted fellow, to the tune of a Turd, or the Black-smith.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Verse: "Did you ne're hear of the baby of Mars ..."</note>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>At foot of text: Imprimat. W.H. R.K. G.B. W.I.</note>
                  <note>Sheet cut and mounted.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jermy, Robert, 1600-1677 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="ballad">
            <pb facs="tcp:182226:1"/>
            <head>A DISPLAY Of the Headpiece and Codpiece VALOUR Of the moſt renowned Colonel <hi>Robert Jermy,</hi> late of <hi>Bafield</hi> in the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> Eſquire, with his Son Captain <hi>Toll</hi> by his ſide, now on their way for <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Or the Lively deſcription of a dead-hearted fellow,</head>
            <opener>to the Tune of a <hi>Turd,</hi> or the Black-Smith.</opener>
            <lg>
               <l>DID you ne're hear of the baby of <hi>Mars,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That charg'd <hi>Tom Fox's</hi> wife with his Tars,</l>
               <l>For his valour lies all in his Arſe.</l>
               <l>Which needs muſt be very ſtrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A Sanctify'd Colonel in beaten Buff,</l>
               <l>With a Scarlet Jump * that's Cudgell proof,</l>
               <l>And his Son<note n="*" place="margin">Cudgeld by Mr. <hi>Armiger</hi> at <hi>Wells</hi> in <hi>Norfolk, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb 4. 1654.</hi> ran away ſix miles at <hi>Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> Se<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge, and neere lookt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him.</note> 
                  <hi>Crowland</hi> Coward of the ſelf ſame ſtuff,</l>
               <l>Who got the wench big with young. <hi>Probatum eſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He's a journey man Souldier to the States Army,</l>
               <l>And 'tis in his terms; when you fight you muſt ſpare me,</l>
               <l>So runs the Commiſſion of Colonel <hi>Jermy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If I be informed true.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Upon a mock Larme he's ſure in the Van,</l>
               <l>Where he takes none, and does no more hurt then he can,</l>
               <l>He's a pitifull Souldier though a Cruell man,</l>
               <l>Let's give the Devill his due.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To Sacrifice to his fears and his pride,</l>
               <l>He caus'd a<note n="*" place="margin">He cauſed Parſon <hi>Cooper</hi> to be hang'd by Judge <hi>Jermy</hi> for fear he ſhould beat him.</note>Church-Champion be murder'd and try'd</l>
               <l>By the Judge of his name, and the rope on his ſide.</l>
               <l>Tis pitty they ever were parted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet you cannot but ſay 'twas very well meant,</l>
               <l>When he went to the houſe of Parliament,</l>
               <l>In Love to his Country before he was ſent</l>
               <l>In a Coach when he might have been Carted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">He corrupted twenty free Burghers at <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> to give their votes for him in the laſt election for Parliament.</note>You muſt alwayes take the good will for the deed,</l>
               <l>Though at <hi>Riſen</hi> he had not the ſuck to ſpeed,</l>
               <l>Yet ſome other place may have very great need,</l>
               <l>If the Devil releaſe but his hire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So dear was his love that he purchas'd a throng,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">He hired <hi>100</hi> men to come with him from <hi>Lyn</hi> with Swords and Guns, for fear Maſter <hi>Howard</hi> and his two men ſhould beat him.</note>Of Sea men in Lice and Lungs very ſtrong,</l>
               <l>Sure he will be ſome body ere it be long,</l>
               <l>If he be not laid in the Mire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How the Sailors did hollow and throw up their hats,</l>
               <l>And the men with wide mouths that uſe to cry Sprats,</l>
               <l>But the brave Spark of <hi>Arndel</hi> made them look like drown'd Rats,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Howard</hi> gave him a box on the ear with the back of his hand, and he fell to the ground with fear.</note>When he humbled <hi>Tom Toll</hi> for his Sin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That high born Heroe had Cudgel'd their Swords,</l>
               <l>Had they not almoſt expit'd at his words,</l>
               <l>But the whole deſign was not worth two half turds,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Guſtice</hi> Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> Peddar, <hi>and</hi> Guſtice Life.</note>Though you throw the three Juſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ices in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In his laſt good ſervice he took the City</l>
               <l>By an Order from the miſtaken Committee,</l>
               <l>Where he ſcap'd a ſcouring the more was the pity,</l>
               <l>For 'twas fowle when you have ſaid what you can.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">He took the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Norwich</hi> when the Gates were open and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> opp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſition.</note>He march'd into Gates with an hundred more,</l>
               <l>O brave! he ne're did the like before,</l>
               <l>For he uſed to ſneak in at the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oxes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ack d<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> back dore,</l>
               <l>As becomes a right modeſt man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When they entred the Town, they beleagur<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Mayor.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:182226:2"/>
               <l> And with wonderfull Courage they ſtormed the Chair,</l>
               <l>But they ſoon were all foul, and ran very fair,</l>
               <l>As if they'd been bred for the Courſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">The Be ls were rung backward which alarmed the City who came in &amp; had beat him if he had not run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way upon the noyſe of it.</note>For the Bells were rung backward as he ſaies his prayers,</l>
               <l>And his head went forward with his haſte down the Staires,</l>
               <l>Like a man of diſpatch in the State Affaires,</l>
               <l>Thank Fortune it was no worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>'Tis much to be wondred he ſhould leave the Rump,</l>
               <l>Though his love to that end has receiv'd a Law Frump,</l>
               <l>But that is his God what ever is trump,</l>
               <l>Yet his Spirit now was blind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Had the Rump but once fizled 'twas the ſtrongeſt ſide,</l>
               <l>But a Fart has ſo routed his Troop in their pride,</l>
               <l>Though infallible<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jermys</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin that prayes and ſwears, and fights and lyes for him in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</note>
                  <hi>Butler</hi> was his guide,</l>
               <l>That they are both blown down the wind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet that would be thought a true<note n="*" place="margin">Let us ſhew our ſelves true Engliſh men is his uſuall ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Engliſh man,</l>
               <l>Let him make true Latine if he can,</l>
               <l>Yet learned mens lives this Raſcall will ſcan,</l>
               <l>And when he has done it deny it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is <hi>Jeremy's</hi> forlorne when brave <hi>Jack</hi> appear.</l>
               <l>He has little of wit, and leſs of fear,</l>
               <l>And ſwears for his Colonel by the year,</l>
               <l>And when he is in he will ply it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When the Nation was Jaded with a<note n="*" place="margin">He that drunk ſo much Aſſes milk as without the Par<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iaments mercy, he is like to be a fool for ever.</note> Quaker,</l>
               <l>This <hi>Jippoe</hi> for-ſooth was a great undertaker,</l>
               <l>And amongſt other Trades a Juſtice maker,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Guſtices <hi>in</hi> Norfolk.</note> 
                  <hi>Brewer, Tirrell,</hi> and Gaffer <hi>Life</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Were made and Created by his ſtinking breath,</l>
               <l>To ſit on the Bench upon life and death,</l>
               <l>We'd as good have had a Turd in our Teeth</l>
               <l>Without any further ſtrife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I thought this Colonel would fayle,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Maſter <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> hath the exemplification of a verdict in a box wherein <hi>Jermys</hi> baude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with <hi>Foxes</hi> wife is ſet forth.</note> When he was upon his Cod piece bayle,</l>
               <l>He got ſuch a flap with a Fox Tayl,</l>
               <l>As more at large in your Box Sir.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now if we may believe Common Fame.</l>
               <l>At preſent they ſay he's fled for the ſame,</l>
               <l>How poorly this fellow has plaid his game,</l>
               <l>But let him not ſcape without knocks Sir.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet he is ſuch a Coward that I dare ſay</l>
               <l>He neither dares fight nor yet run away,</l>
               <l>And yet he'd be glad to ſtand at a ſtay,</l>
               <l>If he might but have his <hi>Quietus.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For tell him his baſeneſſe but once to his face</l>
               <l>Y'are ſure enough he dies on the place,</l>
               <l>If he hangs not himſelf upon this diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Tis One to a Thouſand he'le beat us.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> W. V <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> G. B. W. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
